{"tossups": [{"question": "A holder of this position was exhumed and tried for perjury in the Cadaver Trial. Byzantine governors of the Exarchate of Ravenna once appointed people to this position. Gregory the Great reformed this position, which was supposedly given authority over Western Europe by the Donation of Constantine. In the Great Schism, the holder of this position was excommunicated by the Orthodox Church. For ten points, name this religious position, the head of the Catholic Church.", "answer": "<b> Pope</b> (or<b> Bishop of Rome</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Engravings by William Hogarth are thought to be precursors to these works, especially one wherein the city of London is destroyed in 1720 by the South Sea Bubble. A creator of these works used them to popularize the elephant as a symbol for the GOP. One of these created after the Albany Congress shows a snake cut into 8 pieces and was made by Benjamin Franklin. Thomas Nast created, for ten points, what type of parody artworks often published in newspapers to comment on current events?", "answer": "<b> political cartoon</b>s (prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This U.S. state\u2019s first constitution had a \u201cwhites only\u201d clause. A national park in this state surrounds Mount Mazama, whose caldera filled with water after a prehistoric eruption. A wildlife refuge in this state\u2019s Harney Basin was occupied in 2016 by a group led by Ammon Bundy. The Malheur Wildlife Refuge and Crater Lake are within, for ten points, what Western state whose Willamette Valley was the destination for pioneers traveling a 19th century trail?", "answer": "<b> Oregon</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "In a story set during this conflict, a child falls asleep while playing with a wooden sword in a forest; later, that deaf and mute boy stumbles upon the corpse of his dead parent. During this war, a character is tricked by a disguised scout into attempting to blow up a transportation line, then hallucinates his escape before being hanged for treason. For ten points, name this setting of Ambrose Bierce\u2019s stories \u201cAn Occurrence at Owl Creek Bridge\u201d and \u201cChickamauga.\u201d", "answer": "American<b> Civil War</b> Page 1", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Short Fiction"}, {}, {"question": "A \u201cForum\u201d named after this animal was founded by Phyllis Schlafly to oppose passage of the Equal Rights Amendment. A depiction of this animal on posters was accompanied by the phrase \u201cwe do our part;\u201d that blue type of this animal was the logo of the National Industrial Recovery Act. The lunar module of the Apollo 11 mission bore the name of this animal. For ten points, name this animal, whose bald type is the national emblem of the United States.", "answer": "<b> eagle</b> (accept<b> Eagle</b> Forum; blue<b> eagle</b>s, descriptions of the<b> Eagle</b> module, bald<b> eagle</b>s, etc.; prompt on bird before said)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Description acceptable. The non-fictional Battle of the Windmill took place as part of an effort to achieve this action, which was taken by Hunters\u2019 Lodges in the early 19th century. Isaac Brock\u2019s death at Queenston Heights prevented one of these efforts. John Burgoyne repulsed an earlier attempt at this action during the Revolutionary War, during which Richard Montgomery died. For ten points, name this military action, frequently performed by the early United States, which sought to gain more territory to the north.", "answer": "the U.S.<b> invading Canada</b> (prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The name of this practice was inspired by a Richard Outcault character, a bald child who appeared in<em> Hogan\u2019s Alley</em>. That comic strip ran in both the<em> Journal</em> and<em> World</em>, respectively owned by William Randolph Hearst and Joseph Pulitzer, moguls who perfected this practice. Public support for the Spanish-American War was garnered via, for ten points, what questionable journalistic practice that uses anonymous sources, questionable facts, and sensationalist headlines to sell more newspapers?", "answer": "<b> yellow journalism</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This country launched the Christmas Offensive in a war that began with a border skirmish at Wal Wal. One ruler of this country condemned the use of mustard gas in a speech at the League of Nations. The Derg overthrew a ruler of this country in a communist coup, and Italy annexed this African country prior to World War II. For ten points, name this country, once ruled by Menelik II and Haile [\u201dhighly\u201d] Selassie, whose capital is Addis Ababa.", "answer": "<b> Ethiopia</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "In this battle, John Gordon noted that he had fought his troops \u201cto a frazzle\u201d and required heavy support from James Longstreet. The winning commander in this skirmish was afflicted with a migraine until he received word that the fighting was over; shortly after, Wilmer McLean\u2019s house served as a meeting place. For ten points, name this Civil War battle that took place on the morning of April 9, 1865, a few hours before Ulysses Grant accepted Robert E. Lee\u2019s surrender, effectively ending the war.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Appomattox</b> Court House", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This mountain range was the target of Germany\u2019s Operation Edelweiss in World War II, and its tallest peak was once known as Strobilus. The easternmost end of this mountain range is the Absheron Peninsula. Secessionist republics on the southern slope of this mountain range include Abkhazia and South Ossetia. Mount Elbrus is a part of, for ten points, what mountain chain that runs from the Black Sea to the Caspian Sea, shared by Azerbaijan, Georgia, and Russia?", "answer": "<b> Caucasus</b> Mountains", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "This composer wrote a<em> Te Deum</em> to celebrate the Treaty of Utrecht. The \u201cAir and variations\u201d from this composer\u2019s Suite no. 5 for harpsichord is also known as<em> The Harmonious Blacksmith</em>. This man included a <em>largo al siciliana</em> titled \u201cLa Paix\u201d in a piece written to celebrate the Treaty of Aix-La-Chapelle.<em> Music for</em> <em>the Royal Fireworks</em> was written by, for ten points, what German-born English Baroque composer who also wrote the oratorio<em> Messiah</em>?", "answer": "George Frideric<b> Handel</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "Prior to 594 BC, this city\u2019s ecclesia did not admit thetes, this city\u2019s lowest class. This city\u2019s wealth grew after the discovery of silver at Laurium; Themistocles convinced this city to use that wealth on a new navy, which it promptly used to defeat the Persians at Salamis. The Delian League\u2019s treasury was held in the Parthenon on this city\u2019s Acropolis. For ten points, name this ancient Greek city-state whose wealth funded broad cultural movements and the birth of democracy.", "answer": "<b> Athens</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "One of these structures in Rome is named for Cestius. Another of these structures in North America began slumping by 1200 AD; that structure, Monks Mound, was built in Cahokia. An early form of this structure, Etemenanki, was a temple dedicated to Marduk. Sacrifices to Quetzalcoatl were performed on these structures in Aztec territory, and Chichen Itza was a Mayan example of this structure. Ziggurats were terraced examples of, for ten points, what massive ancient religious structures, commonly built in ancient Egypt?", "answer": "<b> pyramid</b> (prompt on \u201cmound\u201d before mentioned; accept<b> step-pyramid</b><em> after</em> \u201cEtemenanki\u201dis said; prompt on ziggurat<em> after</em> \u201cEtemenanki\u201d is said)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This ruler sought to gain prestige by fighting the War of Devolution against the Triple</b> <b>Alliance. In order to fund his wars against the League of Augsburg and the (+)</b> <b>Grand</b> <b>Alliance, this monarch employed Jean-Baptiste Colbert to manage his kingdom\u2019s finances. A civil war called the Fronde helped this man expand his power into an absolute monarchy. This man brought much of his nobility to the (*) </b> palace of Versailles [vair-sigh]. For ten points, name this Sun King who ruled France for over seventy years.", "answer": "<b> Louis XIV</b> [fourteen] (accept the<b> Sun King</b> until mentioned)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>The \u201cbells were ringing out\u201d for this event as \u201cthe NYPD choir sing[s] \u2018Galway Bay\u2019\u201din The Pogues\u2019 \u201cFairytale of New York.\u201d Another song about this event asks \u201cAnd what have you done?\u201d before commanding \u201cLet\u2019s stop all the fight;\u201d that song parenthetically</b> <b>claims (+)</b> <b>\u201cWar is Over\u201d and is sung by John Lennon, Yoko Ono, and a children\u2019s choir.</b> <b>Bob Geldof organized a 1984 single to raise money for an Ethiopian famine; the title of that song asks (*)</b> \u201cDo They Know It\u2019s\u201d this holiday. For ten points, name this holiday, also the subject of more traditional songs like \u201cCarol of the Bells\u201d and \u201cSanta Claus is Coming to Town.\u201d", "answer": "<b> Christmas</b> (Day and/or Eve; accept \u201cHappy<b> Christmas</b> (War is Over)\u201d; accept \u201cDo They Know It\u2019s<b> Christmas</b>\u201d, and accept it if they finish the lyric, because we\u2019re not really going for the title)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "<b>A popular movement in this state led to the Supreme Court case of</b><em><b> Luther v. Borden </b></em><b>and an uprising put down by a militia called by this state\u2019s governor, Samuel Ward King. Thomas Wilson Dorr fought for democratic reform in this state, which was the site of the</b> <b>Great (+)</b> <b>Swamp Fight and the burning of the</b><em><b> Gaspee</b></em><b> during the colonial era. In the</b> <b>Swamp Fight and the burning of the</b><em><b> Gaspee</b></em><b> during the colonial era. In the</b> <b>1630s, the Narragansett Indians sold the land that would make up this state to (*)</b> <b>1630s, the Narragansett Indians sold the land that would make up this state to (*)</b> Roger Williams. For ten points, name this U.S. state, the site of Providence Plantation and the smallest U.S. state.", "answer": "<b> Rhode Island</b> and Providence Plantations", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>In 1972, dissident poet Pedro Luis Boitel died in one of these events in Cuba. In 1980, one of these events was briefly led by Brendan Hughes; when its demands weren\u2019t met, this</b> <b>event was re-started, and (+)</b> <b>Provisional IRA member Bobby Sands was the first to die.</b> <b>The World Medical Association declares that attempts to forcefully end these events are considered torture, as has been done at (*)</b> Guantanamo Bay using IV bags. For ten points, name this event in which a protester refuses nourishment.", "answer": "<b> hunger strike</b> (accept descriptions; prompt on general terms like \u201c(political) protest;\u201d prompt on descriptions of suicide (attempts)) Page 9", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "<b>One ruler of this dynasty enlisted the help of the Sea Beggars to capture Brielle but was later assassinated by the Catholic extremist Balthasar Gerard. The Duke of Alba established</b> <b>the Council of Blood to quash a revolt by a (+)</b> <b>\u201csilent\u201d ruler of this dynasty during the</b> <b>Eighty Years War. A ruler of this dynasty overthrew James I to become king of (*)</b> England during the Glorious Revolution. William III hailed from, for ten points, what colorfully named royal house of the Netherlands?", "answer": "House of<b> Orange</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>The breakdown of this substance was the subject of the 1987 Montreal Protocol. A 1974 paper by Molina and Rowland explains how this compound could be catalytically broken down by high frequency (+) UV radiation. Each spring, a photochemical reaction depletes this compound in the troposphere over the Earth\u2019s (*) </b> poles. Trichloroethane and other CFCs create \u201choles\u201d in the atmospheric layer of, for ten points, what compound, consisting of three oxygen atoms, which protects Earth from the Sun\u2019s radiation?", "answer": "<b> ozone</b> (accept<b> O</b><u>3</u> before \u201coxygen\u201d is read)", "metadata": "Science - Chemistry"}, {"question": "<b>During this battle, defenders were pocketed in the</b><em><b> Schnee Eifel</b></em> <b>[shnay eye-fell] while defending St. Vith, managing to significantly delay the offensive. Heavy fog prevented effective air cover during the beginning of this battle, which was ended when (+) Patton\u2019s Third Army was able to relieve defending forces. This battle was called Operation Watch on Rhine by its attackers, who were targeting Antwerp. While defending Bastogne [bast-own], General McAuliffe replied (*)</b> \u201cNuts!\u201d to a demand of surrender in, for ten points, what World War II battle in the Ardennes, a German attack that caused a namesake shape in the Allied lines?", "answer": "Battle of the<b> Bulge</b> (accept Operation<b> Watch on Rhine</b> before mention) Page 10", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}], "bonuses": []}